part 2 chapter 9a Winston was gelatinous with fatigue.
Gelatinous was the right word. It had come into his head spontaneously. His
body seemed to have not only the weakness of a jelly, but its translucency.
He felt that if he held up his hand he would be able to see the lights through
it.
All the blood and lymph had been drained out of him by an enormous debauch of
work, leaving only a frail structure of nerves, bones and skin. All sensations
seemed to be magnified. His overalls threatened his shoulders, the pavement
tickled his feet, even the opening and closing of her hand was an effort that
made his joints creak.
He had worked more than 90 hours in five days. So had everyone else in the
Ministry. Now it was all over, and he had literally nothing to do, no Party work of
any description, until tomorrow morning.
He could spend six hours in the hiding place and another nine in his own bed.
Slowly, in mild afternoon sunshine, he walked up a dingy street in the
direction of Mr cherrington's shop, keeping one eye open for the patrols, but
irrationally convinced that this afternoon there was no danger of anyone interfering with him
a heavy briefcase that he was carrying bumped against his knee at each step,
sending a tingling sensation up and down the skin of his leg.
Inside it was the book, which he had now had in his possession for six days and
had not yet opened, nor even looked at.
On the sixth day of Hate Week, after the processions, the speeches, the shouting,
the singing, the banners, the posters, the films, the wax works the rolling of drums
and squealing of trumpets, the of marching feet, the grinding of the
caterpillars of tanks, the roar of masked planes, the booming of guns— —after six
days of this, when the great orgasm was quivering to its climax and the general
hatred of Eurasia had boiled up into such delirium that if the crowd could
have got their hands on the 2000 Eurasian war criminals who were to be
publicly hanged on the last day of the proceedings, they would unquestionably
have torn them to pieces that just this moment it had been
announced that Oceania was not after all at war with Eurasia. Oceania was at war with East Asia
Eurasia was an ally.
There was, of course, no admission that any change had taken place. Merely it
became known, with extreme suddenness and everywhere at once, that East Asia and
not Eurasia was the enemy.
Winston was taking part in a demonstration in one of the central
London squares at the moment when it happened.
It was night, and the white faces and the scarlet banners were liwardly floodless
The square was packed with several thousand people, including a block of
about a thousand school children in the uniform of the Spies. On a scarlet- draped
platform an orator of the Inner Party, a small lean man with disproportionately
long arms and a large bald skull liver which a few length locks straggled, was
haranguing the crowd.
A little Rumpelstiltskin figure, contorted with hatred, he gripped the
neck of the microphone with one hand while the other, enormous at the end of a
bony arm, clawed the air menacingly above his head.
His voice, made metallic by the amplifiers, boomed forth an endless
catalog of atrocities, massacres, deportations, lootings, rapings, torture of
prisoners, bombing of civilians, lying propaganda, unjust aggressions, broken treaties.
It was almost impossible to listen to him without first being convinced and then maddened.
At every few moments the fury of the crowd boiled over and the voice of the
speaker was drowned by a wild beast-like roaring that rose uncontrollably from
thousands of throats.
The most savage yells of all came from the school children
speech had been proceeding for perhaps 20 minutes when a messenger hurried onto
the platform and a scrap of paper was slipped into the speaker's hand. He
unrolled and read it without pausing in his speech.
Nothing altered in his voice or manner, or in the content of what he was saying,
but suddenly the names were different.
Without words said, a wave of understanding rippled through the crowd.
Oceania was at war with East Asia The next moment there was a tremendous
commotion. The banners and posters with which the square was decorated were all wrong!
Quite half of them had the wrong faces on them. It was sabotage! The agents of
Goldstein had been at work!
There was a riotous interlude while posters were ripped from the walls,
banners torn to shreds and trampled underfoot.
The Spies performed prodigies of activity and clambering over the
rooftops and cutting the streamers that fluttered from the chimneys.
But within two or three minutes it was all over. The orator, still gripping the
neck of the microphone, his shoulders hunched forward, his freehand clawing at
the air, had gone straight on with his speech.
One minute more, and the feral Rose of rage were again bursting from the crowd.
The Hate continued exactly as before, except that the target had been changed.
The thing that impressed Winston in looking back was that the speaker had
switched from one line to the other actually in mid-sentence not only
without a pause, but without even breaking the syntax.
But at the moment he had other things to preoccupy him.
It was during the moment of disorder while the posters were being torn down
that a man whose face he did not see had tapped him on the shoulder and said,
'Excuse me, I think you've dropped your briefcase.'
He took the briefcase abstractedly, without speaking. He knew that it would
be days before he had an opportunity to look inside it.
The instant that the demonstration was over he went straight to the Ministry of
Truth, though the time was now nearly 23 hours.
The entire staff of the Ministry had done likewise.
The order is already issuing from the telescreen we're calling them to their
posts, were hardly necessary.
Oceania was at war with East Asia Oceania had always been at war with East Asia
A large part of the political literature of five years was now completely
obsolete. Reports and records of all kinds, newspapers, books, pamphlets, films
soundtracks photographs— —all had to be rectified at lightning speed.
Although no directive was ever issued, it was known that the chiefs of the
Department intended that within one week no reference to the war with Eurasia, or
the alliance with East Asia should remain in existence anywhere.
The work was overwhelming, all the more so because the processes that it
involved could not be called by their true names.
Everyone in the Records Department worked 18 hours in the 24 with two
three-hour snatches of sleep.
Mattresses were brought up from the sellers and pitched all over the
corridors: meals consisted of sandwiches and Victory Coffee wheeled around on
trolleys by attendance from the canteen.
Each time that Winston broke off for one of his spells of sleep he tried to leave
his desk clear of work, and each time that he crawled back, sticky-eyed and
aching, it was defined that another shower of paper cylinders had covered
the desk like a snow drift half burying the speak right and overflowing onto the
floor, so that the first job was always to stack them into a neat enough pile to
give him room to work.
What was worst of all was that the work was by no means purely mechanical.
Often it was enough merely to substitute one name for another, but any detailed
report of events demanded care and imagination.
Even the geographical knowledge that one needed in transferring the war from one
part of the world to another was considerable.
By the third day his eyes ached unbearably and his spectacles needed wiping every few minutes.
It was like struggling with some crushing physical task, something which
one had the right to refuse and which one was nevertheless neurotically anxious to accomplish
insofar as he had time to remember it, he was not troubled by the fact that every
word he murmured into the speak right every stroke of his ink pencil was a deliberate lie.
He was as anxious as anyone else in the Department that the forgery should be perfect.
On the morning of the sixth day the dribble of cylinders slowed down.
For as much as half an hour nothing came out of the tube; then one more cylinder,
then nothing.
Everywhere at about the same time the work was easing off.
A deep and as it were secret sigh went through the Department.
A mighty deed, which could never be mentioned, had been achieved. It was now
impossible for any human being to prove by documentary evidence that the war
with Eurasia had ever happened.
At 1200 it was unexpectedly announced that all workers in the Ministry were
free till tomorrow morning.
Winston, still carrying the briefcase containing the book, which had remained
between his feet while he worked and under his body while he slept, went home,
shaved himself and almost fell asleep in his bath, although the water was barely
more than tepid.
With a sort of voluptuous creaking in his joints he climbed to the stair above
Mr cherrington's shop.
He was tired, but not sleepy any longer.
He opened the window, lit the dirty little oil stove and put on a pan of
water for coffee.
Julia would arrive presently: meanwhile there was the book.
He sat down in the sluttish armchair and undid the straps of the briefcase
A heavy black volume amateuriously bound, with no name or title on the cover.
The print also looked slightly irregular.
The pages were worn at the edges, and fell apart easily, as though the book had
passed through many hands.
The inscription on the title page run THE THEORY AND PRACTICE OF oligarchal
COLLECTIVISM by Emmanuel Goldstein Winston began reading: Chapter 1 Ignorance is Strength.
Throughout recorded time, and probably since the end of the Neolithic Age, there
have been three kinds of people in the world, the High, the Middle and the Low.
They have been subdivided in many ways, they have borne countless different
names, and their relative numbers, as well as their attitude towards one another,
have varied from age to age: but the essential structure of society has never altered.
Even after enormous upheavals and seemingly irrevocable changes, the same
pattern has always reasserted itself, just as a gyroscope will always return
to equilibrium, however far it is pushed one way or the other.
The aims of these groups are entirely irreconcilable....
Winston stopped reading, chiefly in order to appreciate the fact that he was
reading, in comfort and safety. He was alone: no telescreen, no ear at the
keyhole, no nervous impulse to glance over his shoulder or cover the page with his hand.
The sweet summer air played against his cheek. From somewhere far away they
floated the faint shouts of children: in the room itself there was no sound
except the insect voice of the clock.
He settled deeper into the armchair and put his feet up on the fender.
It was bliss, it was eternity.
Suddenly, as one sometimes does with the book of which one knows that one will
ultimately read and reread every word, he opened it at a different place and found
himself at chapter 3.
He went on reading: Chapter 3 War is Peace splitting up of the world into three
great super States was an event which could be and indeed was foreseen before
the middle of the 20th century.
With the absorption of Europe by Russia and of the British Empire by the United
States, two of the three existing powers, Eurasia and Oceania, were already
effectively in being. The third East Asia only emerged as a distinct unit after
another decade of confused fighting.
The frontiers between the three super states are in some places arbitrary, and
in others they fluctuate according to the fortunes of war, but in general they
follow geographical lines eraser comprises the whole of the northern part of the European and
Asiatic land mass from Portugal to the Bering Strait. Oceania comprises the
Americas, the Atlantic islands including the British Isles, Australasia and the
southern portion of Africa East Asia smaller than the others and
with the less definite western frontier, comprises China and the countries to the
south of it, the Japanese islands and a large but fluctuating portion of
Manchuria, Mongolia and Tibet.
In one combination or another, these three super states are permanently at
war, and have been so for the past 25 years.
War, however, is no longer the desperate, annihilating struggle that it was in the
early decades of the 20th century. It is a warfare of limited aims between
competence who are unable to destroy one another, have no material cause for fighting and
are not divided by any genuine ideological difference.
This is not to say that either the conduct of war, or the prevailing
attitude towards it, has become less bloodthirsty or more chivalrous.
On the contrary, war hysteria's continuous and universal in all
countries, and such acts as raping, looting, the slaughter of children, the
reduction of whole populations to slavery, and reprisals against prisoners
which extend even to boiling and burying alive, are looked upon as normal, and, when
they are committed by one's own side and not by the enemy, meritorious.
But in a physical sense war involves very small numbers of people, mostly
highly trained specialists, and causes comparatively few casualties.
The fighting, when there is any, takes place on the vague frontiers whose
whereabouts the average man can only guess at, or around the Floating
Fortresses which guard strategic spots on the sea lanes.
In the centers of civilization war means no more than a continuous shortage of
consumption goods, and the occasional crash of a rocket bomb which may cause a
few scores of deaths.
War has in fact changed its character.
More exactly, the reasons for which war is waged have changed in their order of importance.
Motives which were already present to some extent in the great wars of the
early 20th century have now become dominant and to consciously recognized and acted upon.
To understand the nature of the present war— —for in spite of the regrouping which
occurs every few years, it is always the same war— —one must realize in the first
place that it is impossible for it to be decisive.
None of the three super States could be definitively conquered even by the other
two in combination.
They are too evenly matched, and their natural defenses are too formidable
eraser is protected by its vast land spaces, Oceania by the width of the
Atlantic and the Pacific East Asia by the fecundity and industriousness of its inhabitants.
Secondly, there is no longer, in a material sense, anything to fight about.
With the establishment of self-contained economies, in which production and
consumption are geared to one another, the scramble for markets which was a
main cause of previous wars has come to an end, while the competition for raw
materials is no longer a matter of life and death.
In any case each of the three super States is so vast that it can obtain
almost all the materials that it needs within its own boundaries
insofar as the war has a direct economic purpose, it is a war for labor power.
Between the frontiers of the super States and not permanently in the
possession of any of them, there lies a rough quadrilateral with its corners of
Tangier brotherville Darwin and Hong Kong, containing within it about a fifth
of the population of the earth.
It is for the possession of these thickly- populated regions, and of the
northern ice cap that the three powers are constantly struggling.
In practice no one power ever controls the whole of the disputed area. Portions
of it are constantly changing hands, and it is the chance of seizing this or that
fragment by a sudden stroke of treachery that dictates the endless changes of alignment.
All of the disputed territories contain valuable minerals, and some of them yield
important vegetable products such as rubber which in colder climates it is
necessary to synthesize by comparatively expensive methods.
But above all they contain a bottomless reserve of cheap labor
Whichever power controls equatorial Africa, or the countries of the Middle
East, or Southern India, or the Indonesian Archipelago, disposes also of the bodies
of scores of hundreds of millions of yield paid and hard-working coulies
The inhabitants of these areas, reduced more or less openly to the status of
slaves passed continually from conqueror to conqueror, and are expended like so
much coal or oil in the race to turn out more armaments, to capture more territory,
to control more labor power, to turn out more armaments, to capture more territory,
and so on indefinitely.
It should be noted that the fighting never really moves beyond the edges of the disputed areas.
The frontiers of Eurasia flow back and forth between the basin of the Congo and
the northern shore of the Mediterranean; the islands of the Indian Ocean under
the Pacific are constantly being captured and recaptured by Oceania or by East Asia
in Mongolia the dividing line between Eurasia and East Asia is never stable;
round of the Pole all three powers lay claim to enormous territories which in
fact are largely uninhabited and unexplored: but the balance of power
always remains roughly even, and the territory which forms the heartland of
each super State always remains inviolate. Moreover, the labor of the
exploited peoples around the Equator is not really necessary to the world's
economy. They had nothing to the wealth of the world, since whatever they produce
is used for purposes of war, and the object of waging a war is always to be
in a better position in which to wage another war.
By their labor the slave populations allow the tempo of continuous warfare to be speeded up.
But if they did not exist, the structure of world society, and the process by
which it maintains itself, would not be essentially different.
The primary aim of modern warfare (in accordance with the principles of
doublethink, this aim is simultaneously recognized and not recognized by the
directing brains of the Inner Party) is to use up the products of the machine
without raising the general standard of living.
Ever since the end of the 19th century, the problem of what to do with the
surplus of consumption goods has been latent in industrial society.
At present, when few human beings even have enough to eat, this problem is
obviously not urgent, and it might not have become so, even if no artificial
processes of destruction had been at work.
The world of today is a bare, hungry, dilapidated place compared with the
world that existed before 1914,. and still more so if compared with the
imaginary future to which the people of that period looked forward.
In the early 20th century, the vision of a future society unbelievably rich,
leisured, orderly and efficient— —a glittering antiseptic world of glass and
steel and Snow White concrete— —was part of the consciousness of nearly every literate person.
Science and technology were developing at a prodigious speed, and it seemed
natural to assume that they would go on developing.
This failed to happen, partly because of the impoverishment caused by a long
series of wars and revolutions, partly because scientific and technical
progress depended on the empirical habit of thought, which could not survive in a
strictly regimented society.
As a whole the world is more primitive today than it was 50 years ago. Certain
backward areas have advanced, and various devices, always in some way connected
with warfare and police espionage, have been developed, but experiment and
invention have largely stopped, and the ravages of the atomic war of the 1950s
have never been fully repaired.
Nevertheless the dangers inherent in the machine are still there. From the moment
when the machine first made its appearance it was clear to all thinking
people that the need for human drudgery, and therefore to a great extent for
human inequality, had disappeared. If the machine were used deliberately for that
end, hunger, overwork, dirt, illiteracy and disease could be eliminated within a few
generations.
And in fact, without being used for any such purpose, but by a sort of automatic
process— —by producing wealth which it was sometimes impossible not to distribute—
—the machine did raise the living standards of the average human being
very greatly over a period of about 50 years at the end of the 19th and the
beginning of the 20th centuries.
But it was also clear that an all-round increase in wealth threatened the
destruction— —indeed, in some sense was the destruction— —of a hierarchical society.
In a world in which everyone worked short hours, had enough to eat, lived in a
house with a bathroom and a refrigerator, and possessed a motor car or even an airplane
the most obvious and perhaps the most important form of inequality would
already have disappeared. If it once became general, wealth would confer no distinction.
It was possible, no doubt, to imagine a society in which wealth, in the sense of
personal possessions and luxuries, should be evenly distributed, while power
remained in the hands of a small privileged cast But in practice such a society could not
long remain stable.
For if leisure and security were enjoyed by all alike, the great massive human
beings were normally stupefied by poverty would become literate and would
learn to think for themselves; and when once they had done this, they would
sooner or later realize that the privileged minority had no function, and
they would sweep it away.
In the long run, a hierarchical society was only possible on the basis of poverty and ignorance.
To return to the agricultural past, as some thinkers about the beginning of the
20th century dreamed of doing, was not a practicable solution.
It conflicted with the tendency towards mechanization which had become
quasi-instinctive throughout almost the whole world, and moreover, any country
which remained industrially backward was helpless in a military sense and was
bound to be dominated, directly or indirectly, by its more advanced rivals.
Nor was it a satisfactory solution to keep the masses in poverty by
restricting the output of goods.
This happens to a great extent during the final phase of capitalism, roughly
between 1920 and 1940.. The economy of many countries was allowed to stagnate,
land went out of cultivation, capital equipment was not added to, great blocks
of the population were prevented from working and kept half alive by State charity.
But this, too, entailed military weakness, and since the privations it inflicted
were obviously unnecessary, it made opposition inevitable. The problem was
how to keep the wheels of industry turning without increasing the real wealth of the world.
Goods must be produced, but they must not be distributed. And in practice the only
way of achieving this was by continuous warfare.
The essential act of war is destruction, not necessarily of human lives, but of
the products of human labor War is a way of shattering to pieces, or
pouring into the stratosphere, or sinking in the depths of the sea, materials which
might otherwise be used to make the masses too comfortable, and hence, in the
long run, too intelligent.
Even when weapons of war are not actually destroyed, their manufacturer is
still a convenient way of expending Labor power without producing anything
that could be consumed the Floating Fortress, for example, has locked up in it
the labor that would build several hundred cargo ships. Ultimately it is
scrapped as obsolete, never having brought any material benefit to anybody,
and with further enormous labors and other Floating fortresses built.
In principle the war effort is always so planned as to eat up any surplus that
might exist after meeting the bare needs of the population.
In practice the needs of the population are always underestimated, with the
result that there is a chronic shortage of half the necessities of life;
but this is looked on as an advantage.
It is deliberate policy to keep even the favored groups somewhere near the brink
of hardship, because a general state of scarcity increases the importance of
small privileges and thus magnifies the distinction between one group and another.
By the standards of the early 20th century, even a member of the Inner Party
lives an austere, laborious kind of life.
Nevertheless, the few luxuries that he does enjoy— —his large well-appointed flat,
the better texture of his clothes, the better quality of his food and drink and
tobacco is two or three servants, his private motor car or helicopter— —set him
in a different world from a member of the Outer Party, and the members of the
Outer Party have a similar advantage in comparison with the submerged masses
whom we call 'the proles'.
The social atmosphere is that of a besieged city, where the position of a
lump of horse flesh makes the difference between wealth and poverty.
And at the same time the consciousness of being at war, and therefore in danger,
makes the handing over of all power to a small cast seem the natural, unavoidable
condition of survival.
War, it will be seen accomplishes the necessary destruction, but accomplishes
it in a psychologically acceptable way.
In principle it would be quite simple to waste to the surplus labor of the world
by building temples and pyramids, by digging holes and filling them up again,
or even by producing vast quantities of goods and then setting fire to them. But
this would provide only the economic and not the emotional basis for a hierarchical society.
What is concerned here is not the morale of masses, whose attitude is unimportant
so long as they are kept steadily at work, but the morale of the Party itself.
Even the humblest Party member is expected to be competent, industrious and
even intelligent within narrow limits, but it is also necessary that he should
be a credulous and ignorant fanatic whose prevailing moods of fear, hatred,
adulation and orgiastic triumph.
In other words it is necessary that he should have the mentality appropriate to a state of war.
It does not matter whether the war is actually happening, and, since no decisive
victory is possible, it does not matter whether the war is going well or badly.
All that is needed is that a state of war should exist splitting of the intelligence which the
Party requires of its members, and which is more easily achieved in an atmosphere
of war, is now almost universal, but the higher up the ranks one goes, the more
marked it becomes.
It is precisely in the Inner Party that war hysteria and hatred of the enemy are strongest.
In his capacity as an administrator, it is often necessary for a member of the
uni Party to know that this or that item of war news is untruthful, and he may
often be aware that the entire war is spurious and is either not happening or
is being waged for purposes quite other than the declared ones:
but such knowledge is easily neutralized by the technique of double think
Meanwhile no Inner Party member waivers for an instant in his mystical belief
that the war is real, and that it is bound to end victoriously, with Oceania
the undisputed master of the entire world.
All members of the Inner Party believe in this coming conquest as an article of faith
to be achieved either by gradually acquiring more and more territory and so
building up an overwhelming preponderance of power, or by the
discovery of some new and unanswerable weapon.
The search for new weapons continues unceasingly, and is one of the very few
remaining activities in which the inventive or speculative type of mind can find any outlet.
In Oceania at the present day, Science, in the old sense, has almost ceased to exist.
In Newspeak there is no word for 'Science'.
The empirical method of thought, on which all the scientific achievements of the
past were founded, is opposed to the most fundamental principles of inksock
And even technological progress only happens when its products can in some
way be used for the diminution of human liberty.
In all the useful arts the world is either standing still or going backwards.
The fields are cultivated with horsepower while books are written by machinery.
But in matters of vital importance meaning in effect, war and police
espionage— —the empirical approach is still encouraged, or at least tolerated.
The two aims of the Party are to conquer the whole surface of the earth and to
extinguish once and for all the possibility of Independence thought.
There are therefore two great problems which the Party is concerned to solve.
One is hard to discover, against his will, what another human being is thinking, and
the other is how to kill several hundred million people in a few seconds without
giving warning beforehand insofar as scientific research still
continues, this is its subject matter.
The scientist of today is either a mixture of psychologist and inquisitor,
studying with real ordinary minuteness the meaning of facial expressions,
gestures and tones of voice, and testing the truth producing effects of drugs,
shock therapy, hypnosis and physical torture; or he is chemist, physicist or biologist
concerned only with such branches of his special subject as irrelevant to the taking of life.
In the vast laboratories of the Ministry of Peace, and in the experimental
stations hidden in the Brazilian forests, or in the Australian desert, or on lost
islands of the Antarctic, the teams of experts are inter-fatigably at work.
Some are concerned simply with planning the logistics of future wars; others
devise larger and larger rocket bombs, more and more powerful explosives, and
more and more impenetrable armor plating; others search for new and deadlier gases,
or for soluble poisons capable of being produced in such quantities as to
destroy the vegetation of whole continents, or for breeds of disease
germs immunized against all possible antibodies; others strive to produce a vehicle that
shall bore its way under the soil like a submarine under the water, or an airplane
is independent of its base as a sailing ship; others explore even remote
possibilities such as focusing the sun's rays through lenses suspended thousands
of kilometers away in space, or producing artificial earthquakes and tidal waves
by tapping the heat at the earth's center But none of these projects ever comes
anywhere near realization and none of the three super States ever gains a
significant lead on the others.
What is more remarkable is that all three powers already possess, in the
atomic bomb, a weapon far more powerful than any of that their present
researchers are likely to discover.
Although the Party, according to its habit, claims the invention for itself,
atomic bombs first appeared as early as the 1940s and were first used on a large
scale about 10 years later.
At that time some hundreds of bombs were dropped on industrial centers chiefly in
European Russia, Western Europe and North America.
The effect was to convince the ruling groups of all countries that a few more
atomic bombs would mean the end of organized society, and hence of their own power.
Thereafter, although no formal agreement was ever made or hinted at, no more bombs
were dropped. All three powers merely continued to produce atomic bombs and
store them up against the decisive opportunity which they all believe will come sooner or later.
And meanwhile the art of war has remained almost stationary for 30 or 40 years.
Helicopters are more used than they were formally bombing plants have been
largely superseded by self-propelled projectiles, and the fragile movable
battleship has given way to the almost unsinkable Floating Fortress;
but otherwise there has been little development.
The tank, the submarine, the torpedo, the machine gun even the rifle and the hand
grenade are still in use.
And in spite of the endless slaughters reported in the press and on the
telescreens, the desperate battles of earlier wars, in which hundreds of
thousands or even millions of men were often killed in a few weeks, have never been repeated.
None of the three super States ever attempt any maneuver which involves the
risk of serious defeat whenever any large operation is undertaken, it is usually a surprise
attack against an ally.
The strategy that all three powers are following, or pretend to themselves that
they are following, is the same.
The plan is, by a combination of fighting, bargaining and well-timed strokes of
treachery, to acquire a ring of bases completely encircling one or other of
the rival states, and then to sign a pact of friendship with that rival and remain
on peaceful terms for so many years as to allow suspicion to sleep.
During this time rockets loaded with atomic bombs can be assembled at all the
strategic spots; finally they will all be fired simultaneously, with effects so
devastating as to make retaliation impossible.
It will then be time to sign a pact of friendship with the remaining world
power in preparation for another attack.
This scheme, it is hardly necessary to say, is a mere daydream, impossible realization
Moreover, no fighting ever occurs except in the disputed areas around the Equator and the Pole:
no invasion of enemy territory is ever undertaken.
This explains the fact that in some places the frontiers between the super states are arbitrary.
Eurasia, for example, could easily conquer the British Isles, which are
geographically part of Europe, or on the other hand it would be possible for Oceania to push its
frontiers to the Rhine or even to the Vistula. But this would violate the
principle, followed on all sides though never formulated, of cultural integrity.
If Oceania were to conquer the areas that used once to be known as France and
Germany, it would be necessary either to exterminate the inhabitants, a task of
great physical difficulty, or to assimilate a population of about 100
million people, who, so far as technical development goes, are roughly on the Oceanic level.
The problem is the same for all three super states It is absolutely necessary
to their structure that there should be no contact with foreigners, except, to a
limited extent, with war prisoners and colored slaves. Even the official ally of
the moment is always regarded with the darkest suspicion.
War prisoners apart, the average citizen of Oceania never sets eyes on a citizen
of either Eurasia or East Asia and he has forbidden the knowledge of foreign languages.
If he were allowed contact with foreigners he would discover that they
are creatures similar to himself and that most of what he has been told about them is lies
sealed world in which he lives would be broken, and the fear, hatred and
self-righteousness on which his morale depends might evaporate.
It is therefore realized on all sides that however often Persia, or Egypt, or
Java or Salon may change hands, the main frontiers must never be crossed by
anything except bombs.
Under this lies effect never mentioned aloud, but tacitly understood and acted
upon: namely, that the conditions of life in all three super states are very much the same.
In Oceania the prevailing philosophy is called insock in Eurasia it is called
Neo-Bolshevism, and in East Asia it is called by a Chinese name usually
translated as death worship but perhaps better rendered as Obliteration of the Self.
The citizen of Oceania is not allowed to know anything of the tenets of the other
two philosophies, but he is taught to execrate them as barbarous outrages upon
morality and common sense.
Actually the three philosophies are barely distinguishable, and the social
systems which they support are not distinguishable at all.
Everywhere there is the same pyramidal structure, the same worship of
semi-divine leader, the same economy existing by and for continuous warfare.
It follows that the three super States not only cannot conquer one another, but
would gain no advantage by doing so. On the contrary, so long as they remain in
conflict they prop one another up, like three sheaves of corn.
And, as usual, the ruling groups of all three powers are simultaneously aware
and unaware of what they are doing.
Their lives are dedicated to world conquest, but they also know that it is
necessary that the war should continue everlastingly and without victory.
Meanwhile the fact that there is no danger of conquest makes possible the
denial of reality which is the special feature of ingstock and its rival
systems of thought. Here it is necessary to repeat what has been said earlier,
that by becoming continuous war has fundamentally changed its character.
In past ages of war, almost by definition, was something that sooner or later came
to an end, usually an unmistakable victory or defeat.
In the past, also, war was one of the main instruments by which human societies
were kept in touch with physical reality.
All rulers in all ages have tried to impose a false view of the world upon
their followers, but they could not afford to encourage any illusions that
tended to impair military efficiency.
So long as defeat meant the loss of independence, or some other results
generally held to be undesirable, the precautions against defeat had to be serious.
Physical facts could not be ignored. In philosophy, or religion, or ethics, or
politics, two and two might make five, but when one was designing a gun or an
airplane they had to make four.
Inefficient nations were always conquered sooner or later, and the
struggle for efficiency was inimical to illusions.
Moreover, to be efficient it was necessary to be able to learn from the
past, which meant having a fairly accurate idea of what had happened in the past.
Newspapers and history books were, of course, always colored and biased, but
falsification of the kind that is practiced today would have been impossible
Moore was the sure safeguard of sanity, and so far as the ruling classes were
concerned it was probably the most important of all safeguards.
While wars could be won or lost, no ruling class could be completely irresponsible.
But when war becomes literally continuous, it also ceases to be dangerous.
When war is continuous there is no such thing as military necessity.
Technical progress consists into the most palpable facts can be denied or disregarded.
As we have seen researchers that could be called scientific are still carried
out for the purposes of war, but they are essentially a kind of daydreaming, and
their failure to show results is not important.
Efficiency, even military efficiency, is no longer needed. Nothing is efficient in
Oceania except the Thought Police.
Since each of the three super States is unconquerable, each year is in effect a
separate universe within which almost any perversion of thought can be safely practiced
Reality only exerts its pressure through the needs of everyday life— —the need to
eat and drink, to get shelter and clothing, to avoid swallowing poison or
stepping out of top story windows under the like.
Between life and death between physical pleasure and physical pain, there is
still a distinction, but that is all. Cut off from contact with the outer world,
and with the past, the citizen of Oceania is like a man in interstellar space, who
has no way of knowing which direction is up and which is down.
The rulers of such a state are absolute, as the Pharaohs or the Caesars could not
be. They are obliged to prevent their followers from starving to death in
numbers large enough to be inconvenient, and they are obliged to remain at the
same low level of military technique as their rivals; but once that minimum is
achieved, they can twist reality into whatever shape they choose.
The war, therefore, if we judge it by the standards of previous wars, is merely an imposter
It is like the battles between certain ruminant animals whose horns are set at
such an angle that they are incapable of hurting one another.
But though it is unreal it is not meaningless. It heats up the surplus of
consumable goods, and it helps to preserve the special mental atmosphere
that a hierarchical society needs more it will be seen as now a purely internal
affair. In the past, the ruling groups of all countries, although they might
recognize their common interest and therefore limit the destructiveness of
war, did fight against one another, and the victor always plundered the vanquished.
In our own day they are not fighting against one another at all. The war is
waged by each ruling group against its own subjects, and the object of the war
is not to make or prevent conquests of territory, but to keep the structure of society intact.
The very word 'war', therefore, has become misleading.
It would probably be accurate to say that by becoming continuous war has
ceased to exist. The peculiar pressure that it exerted on human beings between
the Neolithic Age and the early 20th century has disappeared and been
replaced by something quite different.
The effect would be much the same if the three super States instead of fighting
one another, should agree to live in perpetual peace, each inviolet within its own boundaries.
For in that case each would still be a self-contained universe, freed forever
from the sobering influence of external danger.
A piece that was truly permanent would be the same as a permanent war. This—
—although the vast majority of Party members understand it only in a
shallower sense— —is the inner meaning of the Party slogan: War is Peace.
Winston stopped reading for a moment.
Somewhere in remote distance a rocket bomb thundered.
The blissful feeling of being alone with the forbidden book, in a room with no
telescreen, had not worn off.
Solitude and safety were physical sensations, mixed up somehow with the
tiredness of his body, the softness of the chair, the touch of the faint breeze
from the window that played upon his cheek.
The book fascinated him, or more exactly it reassured him.
In a sense it told him nothing that was new, but that was part of the attraction.
It said what he would have said, if it had been possible for him to set his
scattered thoughts in order.
It was the product of a mind similar to his own, but enormously more powerful,
more systematic, less fear-ridden The best books, he perceived, are those
that tell you what you know already.
He had just turned back to Chapter one when he heard Julia's footstep on the
stair and started out of his chair to meet her.
She dumped her brown tool bag on the floor and flung herself into his arms. It
was more than a week since they had seen one another.
'I've got the book,'' he said as they disentangled themselves.
'Oh, you've got it? Good,' she said without much interest, and almost immediately
knelt down beside the oil stove to make the coffee.
They did not return to the subject until they had been in bed for half an hour.
The evening was just cool enough to make it worthwhile to pull up the counterpane.
From below came the familiar sound of singing and the scrape of boots on the
flagstones. The brawny red-armed woman whom Winston had seen there on his first
visit was almost a fixture in the yard.
There seemed to be no hour of daylight when she was not marching to and fro
between the wash tub and the line, alternately gagging herself with clothes
pigs and breaking forth into lusty song.
Julia had settled down on her side and seemed to be already on the point of falling asleep.
He reached out for the book, which was lying on the floor, and sat up against
the Bed Head We must read it,' he said. 'You too. All
members of the Brotherhood have to read it.'
'You read it,' she said with her eyes shut.
'Read it aloud. That's the best way. Then you can explain it to me as you go.'
The clock's hands said six, meaning eighteen. They had three or four hours
ahead of them. He propped the book against his knees and began reading: Chapter one
Ignorance is Strength.
Throughout recorded time, and probably since the end of the Neolithic Age, there
have been three kinds of people in the world, the High, the Middle and the Low.
They have been subdivided in many ways, they have borne countless different
names, and their relative numbers, as well as their attitude towards one another,
have varied from age to age: but the essential structure of society has never
altered. Even after enormous upheavals and seemingly irrevocable changes, the
same pattern has always reasserted itself, just as a gyroscope will always
return to equilibrium, however far it has pushed one way or the other.
'Julia, are you awake?' said Winston.
'Yes, my love, I'm listening. Go on. It's marvelous He continued reading:
The aims of these three groups are entirely irreconcilable. The aim of the
High is to remain where they are. The aim of the Middle is to change places with
the High. The aim of the Low, when they have a name
for it is an abiding characteristic of the law that they are too much crushed
by drudgery to be more than intermittently conscious of anything outside their daily lives—
—is to abolish all distinctions and create a society in which all men shall be equal.
Thus throughout history a struggle which is the same in its main outlines it
occurs over and over again.
For long periods the High seemed to be securely in power, but sooner or later
there always comes a moment when they lose either their belief in themselves
or their capacity to govern efficiently, or both.
They are then overthrown by the Middle, who enlist the law on their side by
pretending to them that they are fighting for liberty and justice.
As soon as they have reached their objective, the Middle thrusts the Low
back into their older position of servitude, and themselves has become the High.
Presently a new Middle group splits off from one of the other groups, or from
both of them, and the struggle begins over again.
Of the three groups, only the lower never even temporarily successful in achieving
their aims. It would be an exaggeration to say that throughout history there has
been no progress of a material kind.
Even today, in a period of decline, the average human being is physically better
off than he was a few centuries ago. But no advance in wealth, no softening of
manners, no reform or revolution has ever brought human equality a millimeter nearer.
From the point of view of the Low, no historic change has ever meant much more
than a change in the name of their masters.
By the late 19th century the recurrence of this patent had become obvious to many observers
they then Rose schools of thinkers who interpreted history as a cyclical
process and claimed to show that inequality was the unalterable law of human life.
This doctrine, of course, had always had its adherence but in the manner in which
it was now put forward there was a significant change.
In the past the need for a hierarchical form of society had been the doctrine
specifically of the High.
It had been preached by kings and aristocrats and by the priest's lawyers
and the like who were parasitical upon them, and it had generally been softened
by promises of compensation in an imaginary world beyond the grave.
The Middle, so long as it was struggling for power, had always made use of such
terms as freedom, justice and fraternity.
Now, however, the concept of human brotherhood began to be assailed by
people who were not yet in positions of command, but merely hoped to be so before long.
In the past the Middle had made revolutions under the banner of equality,
and then had established a fresh tyranny as soon as the old one was overthrown.
The new Middle groups in effect proclaimed their tyranny beforehand.
Socialism, a theory of which appeared in the early 19th century and was the last
link in a chain of thought stretching back to the slave rebellions of
antiquity, was still deeply infected by the Utopianism of past ages.
But in each variant of Socialism that appeared from about 1900 onwards the aim
of establishing liberty and equality was more and more openly abandoned.
The new movements which appeared in the middle years of the century ing soccer
in Oceania, Neo-Bolshevism in Eurasia death worship as it is commonly called,
in East Asia and the conscious aim of perpetuating unfreedom and inequality.
These new movements, of course, grew out of the old ones intended to keep their
names and pay lip service to their ideology.
But the purpose of all of them was to arrest progress and freeze history at a chosen moment.
The familiar pendulum swing was to happen once more, and then stop.
As usual, the High were to be turned out by the Middle, who would then become the High;
but this time, by conscious strategy, the High would be able to maintain their
position permanently.
The new doctrines arose partly because of the accumulation of historical
knowledge, and the growth of the historical sense, which had hardly
existed before the 19th century.
The cyclical movement of history was now intelligible, or appeared to be so;
and if it was intelligible, then it was alterable.
But the principle underlying cause was that, as early as the beginning of the
20th century, human equality had become technically possible.
It was still true that men were not equal in their native talents and that
functions had to be specialized in ways that favored some individuals against others;
but there was no longer any real need for class distinctions or for large
differences of wealth. In earlier ages, class distinctions had been not only
inevitable but desirable.
Inequality was the price of civilization With the development of machine
production, however, the case was altered.
Even if it was still necessary for human beings to do different kinds of work, it
was no longer necessary for them to live a different social or economic levels.
Therefore, from the point of view of the new groups who are on the point of
seizing power, human equality was no longer an ideal to be striven after, but
a danger to be averted. In more primitive ages, when a just and peaceful society
was in fact not possible, it had been fairly easy to believe it.
The idea of an earthly paradise in which men should live together in a state of
brotherhood, without laws and without brute labor had haunted the human
imagination for thousands of years. And this vision had had a certain hold even
on the groups who actually profited by each historical change.
The heirs of the French, English and American revolutions had partly believed
in their own phrases about the rights of man, freedom of speech, equality before
the law, and the like, and had even allowed their conduct to be influenced
by them to some extent.
But by the fourth decade of the 20th century all the main currents of
political thought were authoritarian.
The earthly paradise had been discredited at exactly the moment when it became realizable
Every new political theory, by whatever name it called itself, led back to
hierarchy and regimentation.
And in the general hardening of outlook that set in around about 1930, practices
which had been long abandoned, in some cases for hundreds of years— —imprisonment
without trial, the use of war prisoners as slaves, public executions tortured to
extract confessions, the use of hostages and the deportation of whole populations—
—not only became common again, but were tolerated and even defended by people
who considered themselves enlightened and progressive.
It was only after a decade of national wars, civil wars, revolutions and
counter-revolutions in all parts of the world the dingsok and its rivals emerged
as fully worked out of the political theories.
But they had been foreshadowed by the various systems, generally called
totalitarian, which had appeared earlier in the century, and the main outlines of
the world which would emerge from the prevailing chaos had long been obvious.
What kind of people would control this world had been equally obvious.
The new aristocracy was made up for the most part of bureaucrats, scientists,
technicians Trade union organizers publicity experts, sociologists, teachers,
journalists and professional politicians.
These people, whose origins lay in the salaried middle class and the upper
grades of the working class, had been shaped and brought together by the
barren world of monopoly industry and centralized government.
As compared with their opposite numbers in past ages, they were less avaricious,
less tempted by luxury, hungrier for pure power, and, above all, more conscious of
what they were doing and more intent on crushing opposition.
This last difference was cardinal.
By comparison with that existing today, all the tyrannies of the past were
half-hearted and inefficient. The ruling groups were always infected to some
extent by liberal ideas, and were content to leave loose ends everywhere, to regard
only the overt act and to be uninterested in what their subjects were thinking.
Even the Catholic Church of the Middle Ages was tolerant by modern standards.
Part of the reason for this was that in the past no government had the power to
keep its citizens under constant surveillance.
The invention of print, however, made it easier to manipulate public opinion, and
the film and the radio carried the process further.
With the development of television, and the technical advance which made it
possible to receive and transmit simultaneously on the same instrument,
private life came to an end.
Every citizen, or at least every citizen important enough to be worth watching,
could be kept for 24 hours a day under the eyes of the police and in the sound
of official propaganda, with all other channels of communication closed.
The possibility of enforcing not only complete obedience to the will of the
State, but complete uniformity of opinion on all subjects, now existed for the first time.
After the revolutionary period of the 50s and 60s society regrouped itself, as
always, into High, Middle and Low.
But the new High group, unlike all its forerunners, did not act upon instinct
but knew what was needed to safeguard its position.
It had long been realized that the only secure basis for oligarchy is collectivism.
Wealth and privilege are most easily defended when they are possessed jointly.
The so-called 'abolition of private property' which took place in the middle
years of the century meant, in effect, the concentration of property and far fewer
hands than before: but with this difference, that the new
owners were a group instead of a mass of individuals.
Individually, no member of the Party owns anything, except petty personal belongings.
Collectively, the Party owns everything in Oceania, because it controls
everything, and disposes of the products as it thinks fit.
In the years following the Revolution it was able to step into this commanding
position almost unopposed, because the whole process was represented as an act
of collectivization It had always been assumed that if the capitalist class were expropriated,
Socialism must follow: and unquestionably the capitalists had been expropriated.
Factories, mines, land, houses, transport— —everything had been taken away from them:
and since these things were no longer private property, it followed that they
must be public property insock which grew out of the earlier
Socialist movement and inherited its phraseology, has in fact carried out the main item in
the Socialist program with the result, foreseen and intended
beforehand, that economic inequality has been made permanent.
But the problems of perpetuating a hierarchical society go deeper than this.
There are only four ways in which a ruling group can fall from power.
Either it is conquered from without, or it governs so inefficiently that the
masses are stirred to revolt, or it allows a strong and discontented Middle
group to come into being, or it loses its own self-confidence and willingness to govern.
These causes do not operate singly, and as a rule all four of them are present
in some degree.
A ruling class which could guard against all of them would remain in power permanently.
Ultimately the determining factor is the mental attitude of the ruling class itself.
After the middle of the present century, the first danger had in reality
disappeared. Each of the three powers which now divide the world is in fact
uncontrable and could only become conquerable through its slow demographic
changes which a government with wide powers can easily avert. The second
danger, also, is only a theoretical one.
The masses never revolt of their own accord, and they never revolt merely
because they were oppressed.
Indeed, so long as they are not permitted to have standards of comparison, they
never even become aware that they are oppressed.
The recurrent economic crises of past times were totally unnecessary and are
not now permitted to happen, but other and equally large dislocations can and
do happen without having political results, because there is no way in which
discontent can become articulate.
As for the problem of overproduction, which has been latent in our society
since the development of machine technique, it is solved by the divisive
continuous warfare C Chapter 3. which is also useful in keying up public morale
to the necessary pitch.
From the point of view of our present rule is therefore, the only genuine
dangers of the splitting off of a new group of able underemployed power-hungry
people, and the growth of liberalism and skepticism in their own ranks.
The problem, that is to say, is educational.
It is a problem of continuously molding the consciousness both of the directing
group and of the larger executive group that lies immediately below it.
The consciousness of the masses needs only to be influenced in a negative way.
Given this background, one could infer, if one did not know it already, the general
structure of Oceanic society.
At the apex of the pyramid comes Big Brother.
Big Brother is infallible and all-powerful Every success, every achievement, every
victory, every scientific discovery, all knowledge, all wisdom, all happiness, all
virtue, are held to issue directly from his leadership and inspiration.
Nobody has ever seen Big Brother. He has a face on the hoardings, a voice on the
telescreen. We may be reasonably sure that he will never die, and there is
already considerable uncertainty as to when he was born.
Big Brother is the guys in which the Party chooses to exhibit itself to the world.
His function is to act as a focusing point for love, fear and reverence,
emotions which are more easily felt towards an individual than towards an organization
Below Big Brother comes the Inner Party, its numbers limited to six millions, or
something less than two percent of the population of Oceania.
Below the Inner Party comes the Outer Party, which, if the Inner Party is
described as the brain of the State, may be justly likened to the hands. Below
that come the dumb masses whom we habitually refer to as 'the pros
numbering perhaps 85 percent of the population.
In the terms of our earlier classification, the pearls of the Low:
for the slave population of the equatorial lands, who pass constantly
from conqueror to conqueror, are not a permanent or necessary part of the structure.
In principle, membership of these three groups is not hereditary. The child of
the Inner Party parents is in theory not born into the Inner Party.
Admission to either branch of the Party is by examination, taken at the age of 16.
Nor is there any racial discrimination, or any Marx domination of one province by another.
Jews, Negroes, South Americans of pure Indian blood are to be found in the
highest ranks of the Party, and the administrators of any area are always
drawn from the inhabitants of that area.
In no part of Oceania do the inhabitants have the feeling that they are a
colonial population ruled from a distant capital.
Oceania has no capital, and its titular head is a person whose whereabouts nobody knows.
Except that English is its chief lingua franca and new speak its official
language, it is not centralized in any way.
Its rulers are not held together by Blood Ties but by adherence to a common doctrine.
It is true that our society is stratified, and very rigidly stratified,
on what at first sight appear to be hereditary lines.
There is far less to and fro movement between the different groups that
happened under capitalism or even in the pre-industrial age
Between the two branches of the Party there is a certain amount of interchange,
but only so much as we'll ensure that weaklings are excluded from the Inner
Party and that ambitious members of the Outer Party are made harmless by allowing them to rise.
Proletarians, in practice, are not allowed to graduate into the Party.
The most gifted among them, who might possibly become nuclei of discontent, are
simply marked done by the Thought Police and eliminated.
But this state of affairs is not necessarily permanent, nor is it a matter
of principle. The Party is not a class in the old sense of the word.
It does not aim at transmitting power to its own children, as such; and if there
were no other way of keeping the ableist people at the top, it would be perfectly
prepared to recruit an entire new generation from the ranks of the proletariat.
In the crucial years, the fact that the Party was not a hereditary body did a
great deal to neutralize opposition.
The older kind of socialists who had been trained to fight against something
called 'class privilege', assumed that what is not hereditary cannot be permanent. He
did not see that the continuity of an oligarchy need not be physical, nor did
he pause to reflect that hereditary aristocracies have always been short-lived whereas adoptive
organizations such as the Catholic Church have sometimes lasted for
hundreds or thousands of years.
The essence of oligarchical rule is not father to son inheritance, but the
persistence of a certain worldview and a certain way of life, imposed by the dead
upon the living.
A ruling group is a ruling group so long as it can nominate its successes
The Party is not concerned with perpetuating its blood but with perpetuating itself.
Who wields power is not important, provided that the hierarchical structure
remains always the same.
All the beliefs, habits, tastes, emotions, mental attitudes that characterize our
time are really designed to sustain the mystique of the Party and prevent the
true nature of present-to-day society from being perceived. Physical rebellion,
or any preliminary move toward rebellion, is at present not possible.
From the proletarians nothing is to be feared. Left to themselves, they will
continue from generation to generation and from century to century, working, breeding and dying,
not only without any impulse or a bill but without the power of grasping that
the world could be other than it is.
They could only become dangerous if the advance of industrial technique made it
necessary to educate them more highly; but, since military and commercial
rivalry are no longer important, the level of popular education is actually declining.
What opinions the masses hold, or do not hold, is looked on as a matter of indifference.
They can be granted intellectual liberty because they have no intellect.
In a Party member, on the other hand, not even the smallest deviation of opinion
on the most unimportant subject can be tolerated.
A Party member lives from birth to death under the eye of the Thought Police.
Even when he is alone he can never be sure that he is alone.
Wherever he may be, asleep or awake, working or resting, in his bath or in bed,
he can be inspected without warning and without knowing that he is being inspected.
Nothing that he does is indifferent. His friendships, his relaxations, his behavior
towards his wife and children, the expression of his face when he is alone,
the words he matters in sleep, even the characteristic movements of his body, are
all jealously scrutinized Not only any actual misdemeanor but any
eccentricity, however small, any change of habits, any nervous mannerism that could
possibly be the symptom of an inner struggle, is certain to be detected.
He has no freedom of choice in any direction whatever.
On the other hand his actions are not regulated by law or by any clearly
formulated code of behavior In Oceania there is no law.
Thoughts and actions which, when detected means certain death are not formally forbidden,
and the endless purges, arrests, tortures, imprisonments and vaporizations are not
inflicted as punishment for crimes which have actually been committed, but are
merely the wiping out of persons who might perhaps commit a crime at some time in the future.
A Party member is required to have not only the right opinions, but the right instincts.
Many of the beliefs and attitudes demanded of him are never plainly stated,
and could not be stated without laying bare the contradictions inherent in ingstock
If he is a person naturally orthodox a new speaker good thinker he will in all
circumstances know, without taking thought, what is the true belief or the desirable emotion.
But in any case an elaborate mental training, undergone in childhood and
grouping itself around the Newspeak words Crime Stop black white and
doublethink, makes him unwilling and unable to think too deeply on any subject whatever.
A Party member is expected to have no private emotions and no respirates from enthusiasm.
He is supposed to live in a continuous frenzy of hatred of foreign enemies and
internal traitors, triumph over victories, and self-abasement before the power and
wisdom of the Party.
The discontents produced by his bare, unsatisfying life are deliberately
turned outwards and dissipated by such devices as the Two Minutes Hate, and the
speculations which might possibly induce a skeptical or rebellious attitude are
killed in advance by his early- acquired inner discipline.
The first and simplest stage in the discipline, which can be taught even to
young children, is called, in Newspeak Crime Stop Crime Stop means the faculty of stopping
short, as though by instinct, at the threshold of any dangerous thought.
It includes the power of not grasping analogies or failing to perceive logical
errors, of misunderstanding the simplest arguments if they are inimical to
wingstock and if being bored or repelled by any train of thought which is capable
of leading in a heretical direction Crime Stop in short, means protective
stupidity. But stupidity is not enough. On the contrary, orthodoxy in the full sense
demands a control over one's mental processes as complete as that of a
contortionist over his body.
Oceanic society rests ultimately on the belief that Big Brother is omnipotent
and that the Party is infallible.
But since in reality Big Brother is not omnipotent and the Party is not
infallible, there is need for an unwarying moment-to-moment flexibility
in the treatment of facts.
The key word here is black white Like so many news speak words, this word
has two mutually contradictory meanings.
Applied to an opponent, it means the habit of impudently claiming that black
is white, in contradiction of the plain facts.
Applied to a Party member, it means a loyal willingness to say that black is
white when Party discipline demands this.
But it means also the ability to believe that black is white, and more, to know
that black is white, and to forget that one has ever believed the contrary.
This demands a continuous alteration of the past, made possible by the system of
thought which really embraces all the rest, and which is known in news speakers double think
The alteration of the past is necessary for two reasons, one of which is
subsidiary and, so to speak, precautionary.
The subsidiary reason is that the Party member, like the proletarian,
tolerates present-day conditions partly because he has no standards of comparison.
He must be cut off from the past, just as he must be cut off from foreign
countries, because it is necessary for him to believe that he is better off
than his ancestors and that the average level of material comfort is constantly rising.
But by far the more important reason for the readjustment of the past is the need
to safeguard the infallibility of the Party.
It is not merely that speeches, statistics and records of every kind
must be constantly brought up to date in order to show that the predictions of
the Party were in all cases right. It is also that no change in doctrine or in
political alignment can never be admitted. For to change one's mind, or
even one's policy, is a confession of weakness.
If, for example, Eurasia or East Asia whichever it may be) is the enemy today,
then that country must always have been the enemy. And if the facts say otherwise,
then the facts must be altered.
Thus history is continuously rewritten.
This day-to-day falsification of the past, carried out by the Ministry of
Truth it is necessary to the stability of the regime as the work of repression
and espionage carried out by the Ministry of Love.
The mutability of the past is the central tenet of insock Past events, it is argued, have no
objective existence, but survive only in written records and inhuman memories.
The past is whatever the records and the memories agree upon.
And since the Party is in full control of all records, and in equally full
control of the minds of its members, it follows that the past is whatever the
Party chooses to make it. It also follows that though the past is alterable, it
never has been altered in any specific instance.
For when it has been recreated in whatever shape is needed at the moment,
then this new version is the past, and no different past can ever have existed.
This holds good even when, as often happens, the same event has to be altered
out of recognition several times in the course of a year.
At all times the Party is in possession of absolute truth, and clearly the
absolute can never have been different from what it is now.
It will be seen that the control of the past depends above all on the training of memory.
To make sure that all written records agree with the orthodoxy of the moment
is merely a mechanical act. But it is also necessary to remember that events
happened in the desired manner. And if it is necessary to rearrange one's memories
or to tamper with written records, then it is necessary to forget that one has
done so. The trick of doing this can be learned like any other mental technique.
It is learned by the majority of Party members, and certainly by those who are
intelligent as well as orthodox.
In Old speak it is called, quite frankly, 'reality control'.
In Newspeak it is called a double think the double think comprises much else as well
double think means the power of holding two contradictory beliefs in one's mind
simultaneously, and accepting both of them.
The Party intellectual knows in which direction his memories must be altered;
he therefore knows that he is playing tricks with reality; but by the exercise
of double think he also satisfies himself that reality is not violated.
The process has to be conscious, or it would not be carried out with sufficient
precision, but it also has to be unconscious, or it would bring with it a
feeling of falsity and hints of guilt double think lies at the very heart of
inksock since the essential act of the Party is to use conscious deception
while retaining the firmness of purpose that goes with complete honesty.
To tell deliberate lies while genuinely believing in them, to forget any fact
that has become inconvenient, and then, when it becomes necessary again, to draw
it back from oblivion for just so long as it is needed, to deny the existence of
objective reality and all the while to take account of the reality which one
denies— —all this is indispensably necessary.
Even in using the word double think it is necessary to exercise double think
For by using the word one admits that one is tampering with the reality; by a
fresh act of double think one erases his knowledge; and so on indefinitely, with
the lie always one leap ahead of the truth. Ultimately it is by means of
double think that the Party has been able— —and may, for all we know, continue to
be able for thousands of years— —to arrest the course of history.
All past oligarchies have fallen from power either because they ossified or
because they grew soft.
Either they became stupid and arrogant, failed to adjust themselves to changing
circumstances, and were overthrown; or they became liberal and cowardly, made
concessions when they should have used force, and once again were overthrown.
They fell, that is to say, either through consciousness or through unconsciousness.
It is the achievement of the Party to have produced a system of thought in
which both conditions can exist simultaneously.
And upon no other intellectual basis could the dominion of the Party be made permanent.
If one is to rule, and to continue ruling, one must be able to dislocate the sense
of reality.
For the secret of rulership is to combine a belief in one's own
infallibility with the power to learn from past mistakes the need hardly be said that the
subtlest practitioners of doublethink and those who invented doublethink and
know that it is a vast system of mental cheating.
In our society, those who have the best knowledge of what is happening are also
those who are furthest from seeing the world as it is.
In general, the greater the understanding, the greater the delusion: the more
intelligent, the less sane.
One clear illustration of this is the fact that war hysteria increases in
intensity as one rises in the social scale. Those whose attitude towards the
war is most nearly rational are the subject peoples of the disputed territories.
To these people the war is simply a continuous calamity which sweeps to and
fro over their bodies like a tidal wave.
Which side is winning as a matter of complete indifference to them.
They are aware that a change of overlordship means simply that they will
be doing the same work as before for new masters who treat them in the same
manner as the old ones slightly more favored workers whom we
call 'the pros are only intermittently conscious of the war.
When it is necessary they can be prodded into frenzies of fear and hatred, but
when left to themselves they are capable of forgetting for long periods that the
war is happening.
It is in the ranks of the Party, and above all of the Inner Party, that the
true war enthusiasm is found world's Conquest is believed in most
firmly by those who know it to be impossible.
This peculiar linking together of opposites— —knowledge with ignorance,
cynicism with fanaticism— is one of the chief distinguishing marks of Oceanic society.
The official ideology abounds with contradictions even when there is no
practical reason for them.
Thus, the Party rejects and vilifies every principle for which the Socialist
movement originally stood, and it chooses to do this in the name of Socialism.
It preaches a contempt for the working class unexampled for centuries past, and
addresses its members in a uniform which was at one time peculiar to manual
workers and was adopted for that reason.
It systematically undermines the solidarity of the family, and it calls
its leader by a name which is a direct appeal to the sentiment of family
loyalty. Even the names of the four Ministries by which we are governed
exhibit a sort of impudence in their deliberate reversal of the facts.
The Ministry of Peace concerns itself with war, the Ministry of Truth with lies,
the Ministry of Love with torture and the Ministry of Plenty with starvation.
These contradictions are not accidental, nor do they result from ordinary
hypocrisy: they are deliberate exercises in double think For it is only by reconciling
contradictions that power can be retained indefinitely.
In no other way could the engine cycle be broken.
If human equality is to be forever averted it's the High, as we have called
them, are to keep their places permanently— —then the prevailing mental
condition must be controlled insanity.
But there is one question which until this moment we have almost ignored. It is:
why should human equality be averted?
Supposing that the mechanics of the process have been rightly described, what
is the motive for this huge, accurately planned effort to freeze history at a
particular moment of time?
Here we reach the central secret. As we have seen, the mystique of the Party, and
above all of the Inner Party, depends upon doublethink. But deeper than this
lies the original motive, the never questioned instinct that first led to
the seizure of power and brought doublethink, the Thought Police,
continuous warfare and all the other necessary paraphernalia into existence afterwards.
This motive really consists....
Winston became aware of silence, as one becomes aware of a new sound.
It seems to him that Julia had been very still for some time past.
She was lying on her side, naked from the waist upwards, with her cheek pillowed on
her hand and one dark lock tumbling across her eyes.
Her breast rose and fell slowly and regularly.
'Julia.'
No answer.
'Julia, are you awake?'
No answer. She was asleep.
He shuts the book, put it carefully on the floor, lay down and pulled the
coverlet over both of them.
He had still, he reflected, not learned the ultimate secret.
He understood how; he did not understand why.
Chapter 1 like Chapter 3 had not actually told him anything that he did
not know, it had merely systematized the knowledge that he possessed already.
But after reading it he knew better than before that he was not mad.
Being in a minority, even a minority of one, did not make you mad.
There was truth and there was untruth, and if you clung to the truth even
against the whole world, you are not mad.
A yellow beam from the sinking sun slanted in through the window and fell
across the pillow. He shut his eyes.
The sun on his face and the girl's smooth body touching his own gave him a
strong, sleepy, confident feeling.
He was safe, everything was all right.
He fell asleep murmuring 'Sanity is not statistical,' with the feeling that this
remark contained in it a profound wisdom